VAHIDULLAH TAC

Physics-informed, Data-driven Modeling of Elastic and Inelastic Material Behavior

765 532 2780 tacvahid@gmail.com www.tajtac.com github.com/tajtac linkedin.com/in/tajtac

Summary: My research is focused on combining machine learning and constitutive modeling of soft materials. In contrast to most other research in the literature, my modeling approach is characterized by embedding the relevant physics into the formulation of the problem. For example, I developed models of hyperelasticity and viscoelasticity where the conditions of polyconvexity and positivity of energy dissipation are satisfied exactly.

EDUCATION _____

PhD Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN

2021 - now Mechanical Engineering

Dissertation title: Data-driven modeling of biological materials

MSc Middle East Technical University, Ankara, Turkey

2016 - 2019 Aerospace Engineering

Thesis title: Micromechanical modeling of carbon nanotube – polymer composites

BSc Middle East Technical University, Ankara, Turkey

2012 - 2016 Aerospace Engineering

AWARDS &

HONOURS

- TRAvel for CollaborativE Research (TRACER) Award (\$10,000). I was one of the 5 PhD students and postdocs to receive Purdue University's inaugural TRACER award for travel to Stanford University for a collaboration.
- SES Travel Award (\$1,000) from Society of Engineering Science (SES) to attend the Inaugural SES Future Faculty Symposium, 2023.
- Robert J. Melosh Medal for best student paper in computational solid mechanics, Duke University, 2022.
- Ward A. Lambert Graduate Fellowship, Purdue University, 2022
 Ben M. Hillberry Graduate Scholarship (\$3,600), Purdue University, 2022.
- TUBITAK Publication Award, 2020.
- 3rd Place, Individual Aircraft Design Competition 2015-16, American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AIAA).
- 1st Place, METU Engineering Day 2016 Poster Competition.
- **Full scholarship** from the Ministry of Higher Education of Afghanistan for undergraduate studies in Turkey, covering all expenses.

Publications _

[8] V. Tac, M. K. Rausch, I. Bilionis, F. S. Costabal and A. B. Tepole, "Generative hyperelasticity with physics-informed probabilistic diffusion fields," Submitted. 2023.

- [7] V. Tac, M. K. Rausch, F. S. Costabal and A. B. Tepole, "Data-driven anisotropic finite viscoelasticity using neural ordinary differential equations," Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineering, 2023.
- [6] V. Tac, K. Linka, F. S. Costabal, E. Kuhl and A. B. Tepole, "Benchmarks for physics-informed data-driven hyperelasticity," Computational Mechanics, 2023.
- [5] V. Tac, F. S. Costabal, and A. B. Tepole, "Data-driven tissue mechanics with polyconvex neural ordinary differential equations," Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineering, 2022.
- [4] V. Tac, V. D. Sree, M. K. Rausch, and A. B. Tepole, "Data-driven modeling of the mechanical behavior of anisotropic soft biological tissue," Engineering with Computers, 2022.
- [3] Y. Leng, V. Tac, S. Calve, and A. B. Tepole, "Predicting the mechanical properties of biopolymer gels using neural networks trained on discrete fiber network data," Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineering, 2021.
- [2] V. Tac and E. Gürses, "Micromechanical modelling of carbon nanotube reinforced composite materials with a functionally graded interphase," Journal of Composite Materials, 2019.
- [1] W. Taj and D. Coker, "Dynamic frictional sliding modes between two homogenous interfaces", IOP Conference Series: Materials Science and Engineering, 2018.

TEACHING

Fall 2023

ME 270 - Statics I was the instructor for one of the sections of ME 270 - Basic Mechanics I as part of the Ward A. Lambert Teaching Fellowship.

ME 270 - Statics Spring 2023

I taught a few sessions of the class in preparation for my Fall 2023 class.

EXPERIENCE

University

2021 - now

Purdue Research Assistant

• Research on developing data-driven models of hyperelasticity and viscoelasticity. Developed two data-driven models of hyperelasticity using Feed-Forward Neural Networks and Neural ODEs. Developed the first fully data-driven, physics-informed model of anisotropic finite viscoelasticity.

Turkish

Structural Design Engineer

Aerospace

2018 - 2021

 Designed various spacecraft parts such as structural panels, inserts and brackets. Spearheaded the development of the first structural panel with embedded active cooling in TAI.

TUBITAK Space Technologies Research Institute

2017 - 2018

Research Engineer

Developed two engineering software packages for 1) conceptual aircraft design and 2) prediction of failure modes of composite materials.

SKILLS

- Finite Element Method
 - Machine learning & Optimization
 - Programming languages such as Python & FORTRAN
 - Visualization

■ Familiarity with a variety of tools and languages such as Julia, Visual Basic, MATLAB, C, HTML, Javascript, PHP, IATEX and others.